Guide to the William Horace Littlefield Papers Related to "Portrait Drawings of Poets, and Their Manuscripts" Exhibition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Horace Littlefield papers related to "Portrait Drawings of Poets, and Their Manuscripts" exhibition
1932-1977
1941-1947
YCAL MSS 602
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.54
(3 boxes)
The collections consists of artwork, manuscripts, correspondence, and other material relating to William Horace Littlefield's exhibition "Portrait Drawings of Poets, and Their Manuscripts" (1942). The bulk of the collection is comprised of the original portrait drawings and mounted autograph and typescript manuscripts of American and British poets displayed in the exhibit. According to an artist note found in the collection, "the drawings are portrait heads in pencil on grey-green paper, modelled in white and grey, the medium being water in oil tempera. Each is signed and dated by poet and artist." Correspondence includes letters from poets responding to Littlefield's request to sit for a portrait, as well as more general correspondence. Other material includes writings by Littlefield and printed material related to the exhibit.
Littlefield, William Horace, 1902-1969
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Richard Stiner, 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Horace Littlefield (1902-1969)
William Horace Littlefield, American painter, writer, and art collector. Littlefield was born in Roxbury, Massachusetts in 1902, and was educated at Harvard University (A.B., 1924). His exhibition, "Portrait Drawings of Poets, and Their Manuscript" (1942), featured fourteen portraits of contemporary American and British poets displayed in conjunction with autograph and typescript manuscripts of each poet. Featured poets included: William Abrahams, John Peale Bishop, John Malcolm Brinnin, John Ciardi, Richard Eberhart, Dudley Fitts, Robert Hillyers, John Holmes, Samuel French Morse, Howard Moss, Winfield Townley Scott, Theodore Spencer, Dunston Thompson, Robert Penn Warren, and Edward Weismiller.
Scope and Contents
The collections consists of artwork, manuscripts, correspondence, and other material relating to William Horace Littlefield's exhibition "Portrait Drawings of Poets, and Their Manuscripts" (1942). The bulk of the collection is comprised of the original portrait drawings and mounted autograph and typescript manuscripts of American and British poets displayed in the exhibit. According to an artist note found in the collection, "the drawings are portrait heads in pencil on grey-green paper, modelled in white and grey, the medium being water in oil tempera. Each is signed and dated by poet and artist." Correspondence includes letters from poets responding to Littlefield's request to sit for a portrait, as well as more general correspondence. Other material includes writings by Littlefield and printed material related to the exhibit.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Artwork and Manuscripts, 1940-1954. II. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1932-1977.
Painters -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Portraits; Poets, English -- 20th Century -- Portraits; Drawings (visual works); Painters -- United States -- 20th Century; Abrahams, William Miller, 1919-1998; Bishop, John Peale, 1892-1944; Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1916-1998; Ciardi, John, 1916-1986; Eberhart, Richard, 1904-2005; Fitts, Dudley, 1903-1968; Hillyer, Robert, 1895-1961; Littlefield, William Horace, 1902-1969; Morse, Samuel French, 1916-1985; Moss, Howard, 1922-1987; Scott, Winfield Townley, 1910-1968; Spencer, Theodore, 1902-1949; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989; Weismiller, Edward Ronald, 1915-
- Artwork and Manuscripts, 1940-1954; Series I; 4
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by poet.
  - Abrahams, William Miller
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Abrahams. 38 x 55 cm., 1942 May 17
    - "Troop Train," autograph manuscript, 1942 July 17
  - Bishop, John Peale
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Bishop. 40 x 60 cm., 1942 May 15
    - "Crucifixion," autograph manuscript, undated
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Brinnin. 38 x 60 cm., 1942 January 23
    - "Mardi Gras, For John Hensdale Thompson," typescript with autograph corrections, undated
  - Ciardi, John
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Ciardi. 38.5 x 60 cm., 1942 April 23
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Ciardi. 42.5 x 60 cm., 1942 May 29
    - "Suddenly Where Squadrons Turn," autograph manuscript, 1942
  - Eberhart, Richard
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Eberhart. 40 x 52 cm., 1942 April 20
    - "I Walked Out to the Graveyard to See the Dead," autograph manuscript, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Grave Piece," typescript with autograph corrections, undated
  - Fitts, Dudley
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Fitts. 44 x 60 cm., 1945 September 29
    - "Experience in a Coal-Bin. A True Relation," typescript with autograph corrections, undated
  - Hillyer, Robert
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Hillyer. 38 x 51 cm., 1942 April 8
    - "With Every Slash of Rain Against the Window," autograph manuscript, undated
  - Holmes, John
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Holmes. 40 x 61 cm., 1942 May 7
    - "Let the Joyful Speak," typescript with autograph corrections, 1942
    - "Let the Joyful Speak," typescript, 1942 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margules, De Hirsh
    - "Mulbery Bend," autograph manuscript, 1954 May 22
  - Morse, Samuel French
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Morse. 41 x 59.5 cm., 1942 March 18
    - "Lucy and Roger," typescript with autograph corrections, 1941 January-February
  - Moss, Howard
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Moss. 43 x 59.5 cm., 1942 July 25
    - "The Shore Remembered," typescript, undated
  - Scott, Winfield Townley
    - "Natural Causes," typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Scott. 40.5 x 51 cm., 1942 May 16
    - "Natural Causes," autograph manuscript, 1942 May 15
  - Spencer, Theodore
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Spencer. 46 x 60 cm., 1942
    - "Christmas, 1941," autograph manuscript
  - Tate, Allen
    - "Seasonal Confessions," typescript with autograph corrections, 1944 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Thompson, Dunstan
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Thompson. 40 x 60 cm., 1942 April 30
    - "Orphic Song," autograph manuscript, 1942 March 12-13
  - Warren, Robert Penn
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Warren. 46 x 60 cm., 1945 September 8
    - "The Ballad of Billie Potts," typescript with autograph corrections, undated
  - Weismiller, Edward
    - Pencil with water in oil tempera; on gray-green paper. Signed by Littlefield and Weismiller. 40 x 59 cm., 1942 February 13
    - "Wilderness," autograph manuscript, undated
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1932-1977; Series II; 0.16; (1 box)
  Organized by format. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Correspondence
    - Abrahams, William, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aiken, Conrad, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Barker, George, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Berryman, John, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bishop, John Peale, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Blake, Howard, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Boston Public Library, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Brown, Harry, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - University of Buffalo, Lockwood Memorial Library, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ciardi, John, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Eberhart, Richard, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Enoch Pratt Free Library, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Fitts, Dudley, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Gianos, D. H., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Holmes, John, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Littlefield, William Horace, 1945-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mongan, Agnes, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Morrison, Kathleen, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Morse, Samuel French, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Moss, Howard, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Olivet College, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Patchen, Kenneth, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Porter, Kenneth W., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Prokosch, Frederic, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Sarton, May, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Schwartz, Delmore, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Scott, Winfield Townley, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Spencer, Theodore, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Stevens, Wallace, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Sweeney, John, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Tate, Allen, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Untermeyer, Louis, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Warren, Robert Penn, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Weismiller, Edward, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Writings by Littlefield
    - A note by the artist, for an exhibition of his drawings, entitled Portraits of Poets and their Manuscripts, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Addresses and biographical data, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Portrait drawings of poets, and their manuscripts, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Printed Material
    - Brochure on the Enoch Pratt Free Library, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Horizon: a magazine of the arts, 1963 July (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Card: William Horace Littlefield, 1902-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - New York Times Book Review, 1977 January 9
    - Newspaper clipping, 1942 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Oversize, 0.33; (2 boxes)
  - Abrahams, William (from Series I), 1942 May 17 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 51)
  - Bishop, John Peale (from Series I), 1942 May 15 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 52)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm (from Series I), 1942 January 23 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 53)
  - Ciardi, John (from Series I), 1942 April 23 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 54)
  - Ciardi, John (from Series I), 1942 May 29 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 55)
  - Eberhart, Richard (from Series I), 1942 April 20 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Fitts, Dudley (from Series I), 1945 September 29 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 57)
  - Hillyer, Robert (from Series I), 1942 April 8 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 58)
  - Holmes, John (from Series I), 1942 May 7 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 59)
  - Morse, Samuel French (from Series I), 1942 March 18 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 60)
  - Moss, Howard (from Series I), 1942 July 25 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 61)
  - Scott, Winfield Townley (from Series I), 1942 May 16 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Spencer, Theodore (from Series I), 1942 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Spencer, Theodore (from Series I), 1941? (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 64)
  - Thompson, Dunstan (from Series I), 1942 April 30 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Thompson, Dunstan (from Series I), 1942 March 12-13 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Warren, Robert Penn (from Series I), 1945 September 8 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 67)
  - Weismiller, Edward (from Series I), 1942 February 13 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 68)
  - Abrahams, William (from Series I), 1942 July 17 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 69)
  - Bishop, John Peale (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 70)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 71)
  - Ciardi, John (from Series I), 1942 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 72)
  - Eberhart, Richard (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 73)
  - Fitts, Dudley (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 74)
  - Hillyer, Robert (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 75)
  - Holmes, John (from Series I), 1942 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 76)
  - Margules, De Hirsh (from Series I), 1954 May 22 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 77)
  - Morse, Samuel French (from Series I), 1941 January-February (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 78)
  - Moss, Howard (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 79)
  - Scott, Winfield Townley (from Series I), 1942 May 15 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 80)
  - Warren, Robert Penn (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 81)
  - Weismiller, Edward (from Series I), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 82)
  - New York Times Book Review (from Series II), 1977 January 9 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 83)